你好黑客，我的名字是Yan
hello hackers my name is Yan
您正在收看PWN大学
you're watching pwn college
今天我们要讲的是
and today we're talking about
内存信息泄露
memory disclosures
一类特殊的内存错误
a special class of memory errors which
我们会结合本模块讨论过的保护机制来讲解
we'll talk about in the context of all of the defenses that we just discussed
我们讨论了栈金丝雀
we just discussed stack canaries
我们讨论了地址空间布局随机化
we just discussed Address Space Layout Randomization
它们的核心都是秘密
and the core of all of these things is secrets
栈金丝雀是一个秘密值，在函数运行之前写入栈
a stack canary is a secret value that is written to the stack before a function runs
并在函数运行完后进行检查
and is checked after the function runs
它是一个秘密值
and the idea is that it's a secret value
那么攻击者
so the attacker
如果他们可以覆盖栈
if they can overwrite the stack
他们不知道这个秘密值
don't know this secret value
当他们覆盖栈时
and when they overwrite the stack
它会被覆盖成别的东西
they will overwrite it with something else
同样，地址空间布局随机化是一个或一组秘密值
likewise Address Space Layout Randomization is a secret value or a set of secret values
它们是代码和数据这类程序资产在内存中的位置
at which program assets like code and data are laid out in memory
ASLR的安全性建立在攻击者不知道这些偏移
the security of ASLR depends on the attacker not knowing those offsets
所以如果有办法得到这些偏移
so there's a way to get these offsets
这将是一个大问题
then this is a big problem
我们今天要讲的是导致这些信息泄露的内存错误
so we're going to talk about memory errors today that lead to these disclosures
好了，我们开始吧
alright let's roll
第一个超级简单
the 1st one is super easy
缓冲区越界读
buffer overread
从概念上讲，它是缓冲区溢出的读版本
conceptually it's the read version of a buffer overflow
有大量的读取，而不是大量的写入
instead of a large write we have a large read
当然，也可能
of course this can also occur
将数据拷贝到一个攻击者可以输出的地方等等
we have a large copy somewhere else that the attacker can then have printed out to them etc
这是最小的例子
this is the very smallest example
我们有一个小的缓冲区然后我们把这个缓冲区写出来
where we have a small buffer and then we write out that buffer
好了，让我们看看它是怎么工作的
all right let's take a look at how it works in what is written
我创建了这个buffer_overread.c
so yeah I created this buffer_overread.c
就是我们在这里看到的
and it's exactly what we saw there
编译一下
let's compile it
好的，我们运行它
okay we run it
它会像预期的那样打印出一堆垃圾
and it prints out a bunch of garbage as expected right
让我们看看打印出来的是什么
let's take a look at what is printed out
首先，你可以马上看到
1st of all immediately you can see the
这个16字节的小缓冲区
the 16 bytes of this small buffer
里面已经有一半数据了
already half stuff in it
这个有点超前了
this is actually looking ahead
哇，不是这个
whoa not that
这也超前了
looking ahead that's also looking ahead
buffer_overread.c
我们把它初始化为空字节
let's initialize it properly to null bytes
好吧，我们来看看泄露了什么
all right let's let's take a look at what leaked
这是我们16字节的缓冲区，然后
okay so here's our 16 bytes of of buffer and then
还有112个字节的垃圾被打印出来
there's another 112 bytes of garbage that's printed
但这些垃圾不是无用的
but this garbage is far from useless
这里有个地址
there's an address here
所以我们刚刚绕过了ASLR
so we have just broken ASLR
这看起来像一个栈金丝雀值
there this looks like a stack canary
一个空字节开始，然后是一堆其他的东西
starts with a null byte and then a bunch of other stuff
如果我再运行一次，每次都能看到随机结果
that if I run again we can see randomizes every time
我们刚刚泄露了栈金丝雀
we just leaked the stack canary
这看起来像是其他地方的偏移
this looks like an offset somewhere else
我猜这是一个栈偏移
so I'm guessing this is a stack offset
这是一个库函数偏移量，或者反过来
and this is a library function offset maybe or or vice versa
估计是反过来
probably vice versa
这可能是栈上的某个地方
this is probably about somewhere on the stack
不，我还是坚持我最初的判断
nah I'm gonna go with my initial assessment
但
but
你可以看到我们从一个过量读中泄露了很多数据
you can see we are leaking a lot of data from an overread
如果我们同时有过量读和过量写
and then if we had both an overread and an overrite
然后
then
我们可以泄露出栈金丝雀，然后
we could leak out the stack canary and then
当我们进行覆盖时，用正确的值覆盖它
when we do the overwrite write it with a correct value
这样就绕过了栈金丝雀检查
so that the stack canary check passes
或
or
当我们进行覆盖时，我们写入了正确的地址
when we do the overwrite we write the correct address
这样尽管开启了ASLR
so that despite ASLR
还是可以正常工作
we can function properly
好吧，当然我是说
okay and of course I mean
像这个指向哪里等等问题
the question of where does this point and so forth
我们可以通过GDB
we can understand by stepping through in GDB and
看这些数据从何而来，来理解程序
seeing where does data comes from to understand the program
好吧
all right
下一个问题字符串终止符
next problem string termination
字符串终止符是一个非常令人头痛的问题
string termination is a giant headache
字符串在C中没有显式的大小元数据
strings do not have explicit size metadata at C
就像很多其他事情一样
like many other things um
所以那里的C开发人员智慧友善的决定
and so the C developers in there in friend and wisdom decide
这很好解决
okay well this is an easy thing to solve
这是个很容易解决的问题
an easy problem to solve
不传递占用内存的大小元数据
that isn't passing around the size which takes up space and memory
不然你还要跟踪大小等等
and then you have to track the size and so forth
我们规定字符串
we'll just allow strings
是一个字节缓冲区加一个null字节
to be buffers of bytes and at then of that buffer there's a null byte
无论null字节在哪，我们都假设它以null结尾
and wherever the null byte is we'll assume it's null terminated
这就导致了一些问题
so this leads to problems
一个是字符串操作很容易导致溢出
one is it's very easy with a string operation to cause overflows
我们在之前的视频中讨论过这个
right and we talked about this in a in a previous video in this module
但这也很容易导致内存泄露
but it's also very easy to cause memory disclosures
就像列在这里的程序一样
which the program listed here does
这个程序非常简单，它读取一个flag
this program is pretty simple it reads a flag
然后它读取我的名字，然后说你好+名字
and then it reads my name and then it says hello name
这个程序不应该打印flag
right this program shouldn't print me the flag
但我会展示给你看，它会为我打印flag
but I will show you that it will print me the flag
好吧
all right
让我们来看看
so let's take a look
这是程序
here's the program
很简单
nice and simple
umm
so what it it
它将name缓冲区初始化为0
it initializes this to to zero the name buffer
然后它会读入
then it reads into it
然后输出hello name
then it prints hello name
顺便说一句
and as an aside
在这一切之前，它会读入flag
before it all does all this it reads into the flag
所以让我们
so let's
编译一下
let's compile it
运行它
let's run it
哦,这
oh it
这是恼人的
that's annoying
好了它
okay it
让我
let me just
修改一下，输出换行
let's change this to have a new line
这样它才会清空输出这个缓冲区
so that it flushes this buffer
编译它
compile it
这是怎么回事
what's going on what
编译它
compile it
运行它好吧，我叫什么名字，我的名字是Yan
run it okay what's my name my name is Yan
你好,Yan
hello Yan
它有点懒，由新行才输出
okay it's a little lazy it it it got the new line
好的，但有趣的是
all right but the interesting thing here
这个数组的大小是10
is that this array is sized uh uh size 10
然而这里是64
and then there's a size 64 right here
我将读取10个字节
I will read in 10 bytes
那空字节放在哪里呢
so where's the null byte gonna go
这里有一个非常类似的东西
there's a very analogous thing of a little bit
很多这样的终止符问题
a lot of these termination issues
类似于off by one 问题
are analogous to off by one errors
因为如果我读入9字节
because if I'd read 9
我仍然有第10个字节作为终止符
I'd still have one of the initial 10 null bytes
但因为我读入了10字节
but since I read 10
当我给它一堆a
I can give it a bunch of As
这是它打印的东西，你好
and here is what it prints hello
当然对于%s
and of course %s
当他打印时，它会说ok
when it's printing out it says okay
Printf会在这里打印一个字符串
printf is gonna print a string here right
在这里，它说打印一个name指向的字符串，
right here it says print a string point to by name
没有大小元数据
there's no size metadata
而只是一直打印直到遇到一个空字节
other than just keep printing until you find a null byte
问题是我消除了所有的空字节
and the problem is I eliminator all the null bytes
我用这个输入覆盖了它们
I overwrote them with this input
它说，好，你好
and so it says okay hello
然后打印出10个A, 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
and then in prints 10 A's 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
然后继续打印
and then it keeps printing
因为它没有找到一个空字节
because it hasn't found an null byte
栈上name旁边是下一个缓冲区
and next to my name on the stack is this next buffer
flag
that's the flag
突然间我把flag泄露了
and suddenly I've leaked the flag
但同样的，我也泄露了一些其他的东西
but in the same way I've leaked some other stuff too by the way
看看我泄露了什么
let's see what I've leaked
传到hexdump
pipe it to HD
我泄露了
I have leaked
就在这里，看起来像个指针
right here what looks like a pointer somewhere
这
this
现在
now
不，是这个
no, this yeah
所以我泄露了一个看起来像指针的东西
so I've leaked something that looks like a pointer
然后这个换行符的后面就是00（终止符不打印）
and then the ??? point to new line is the end of the thing
所以你也可以泄露内存地址
so you can also leak memory addresses
只要里面不含0
as long as they don't have 0 inside them
这非常酷
which is super cool
提醒一句，你可能马上会想哦
one word of caution you might immediately think ooh
哦哦
ooh ooh
我可以泄露栈金丝雀
I can leak the canary
事实并非如此
that is not the case
金丝雀设计师想到了这一点
the canary designers thought of this
如果你看一下我们的缓冲区过量读的例子
if you look at our buffer overread example
因为这是打印金丝雀的简单方法
because that's an easy way to print the canary
看这个金丝雀
look at this canary
金丝雀从一个空字节开始
the canary starts with a null byte
正是为了这个目的
exactly for this purpose
正是如此，遇到字符串终止问题导致内存泄露时
exactly so that using a string termination issue leading to a memory disclosure
你无法泄露金丝雀值
you cannot leak out the canary
可以看出这类问题很常见
that's how common these types of issues are
金丝雀
that a canary
金丝雀给出了整整一个字节
an entire byte of a canary was given over
来停止这些失控的字符串操作
to stop these runaway string operations
好
all right
最后一个 未初始化的数据
last one uninitialized data
这是漏洞中的一大类
this is a giant class of vulnerability
就其本身而言
on all by itself
回想一下我在本模块开始时说过的
recall as I said in the beginning of this module
C不会为你收拾残局
C will not clean up after you
你得自己收拾干净
you have to clean up after yourself
C很底层
C is extremely low level
你让它做什么它就只会做什么
it will do exactly what you tell it to do
这包括栈
and that includes the stack
当你释放一个栈帧时
when you deallocate a stack frame
没有数据被销毁
no data is destroyed
做的就是改变栈指针的值
all you do is change the value of the stack pointer
还有帧指针的值
and the frame pointer
旧数据还在那里
the old data is there
那么这里发生了什么
so what happens here
我们有一个main函数调用foo，然后调用bar
we have a main that calls foo and then calls bar
在foo中
in foo
它分配一个64字节的缓冲区，并将flag读入其中
it allocates a 64 byte buffer and reads the flag into it
在bar中会把缓冲区写出来
and in bar it writes that buffer out
没有过量读取
there's no over reads
一切都是合法的
everything is legit
问题是
problem is
flag还在内存中
that the flag is still in memory
这是，怎么了
so here's , what's going on
这是uninitialized.c
so here is the uninitialized.c
我们来编译一下这个程序
that exact program let's compile it
运行它
run it
flag和其他一堆垃圾碰巧在栈上
the flag and a bunch of other garbage that happened to be on the stack
这些乱七八糟的存在不是因为读取flag导致过量写入
that wasn't over written by the read of the flag
再次强调，栈本身是一团乱
again the stack is a mess
如果你想确定
if you want to be very sure
你没有使用未初始化数据
that you don't have an initialized data
初始化它
initialize it
如果你想确定
if you want to make very sure
你没在栈上留下秘密，比如flag
that you are not leaving around secrets on the stack in memory such as the flag
显式地删除它们
explicitly erase them
顺便说一下，这也适用于动态内存分配
this also applies by the way to dynamic memory allocation
当你释放一些东西
when you free something
这些数据大部分还保存在内存中
that data mostly stays in memory
如果你malloc了
if you malloced
使用一些东西，然后释放它，数据还会一直存在
use something and then free it that data stays around
我们将在动态分配器误用模块中更详细地讨论这一点
and we'll cover that in much more detail in the dynamic allocator misuse module
我还要提一件事
I'll mention one more thing
即使你试着做一个细心的人
even if you try to be a careful person
然后你意识到
and you realize that hey
我读到的这个flag是敏感的，我应该删除它
this flag I read is sensitive and I should remove it
这里这段代码使用memset
here this code is using memset
memset
为什么不行，好了
why doesn't it okay
Memset将用一个常量字节填充内存
memset wil fill a memory with a constant byte
它会用常量字节c在地址s上写入n个字节
it will location s with byte C for n bytes okay
让我们看看它会做什么
let's take a look at what this does
这应该读入flag
that this should read in the flag
从内存中删除，然后调用bar
wipe it from memory and then call bar
然后写出缓冲区
right and then write out that buffer
现在那里应该都被memset归零了
which now should be all zeroed out from that memset
让我们来看看实际发生了什么
let's take a look at what actually happens
我在uninitialized-safe中实现了这个
right so I implemented this in uninitialized safe
这儿是memset
here it is here's the memset
我们来编译一下
so let's compile it
运行一下，啥也没输出
let's run it nothing
如果你用hexdump查看，都是0
if you hex dump all zeros
64字节的0，你可以看到这个星号，和0x40
64 bytes of zeros you can see this star with a hex 40
十六进制40是64
hex 40 is 64
全是0，太棒了，我们解决了这个问题吗？
it's all zeros awesome did we solve the problem
并没有，这实际上是加密实现中的一个大问题
not really this is actually a huge um problem in crypto implementations
编译器会对代码优化
a compiler that is run with optimizations
当你编译代码时，你一般会启用编译器优化
which typically when you compile code to ship you enable compiler optimization
这样你的代码运行得更快
so that your code runs a lot faster
（编译器）会认为你写的memset毫无意义
will decide that hey this memset it's pointless
为什么它毫无意义
why is it pointless
因为这是一个局部变量，在这个memset之后就不用了
because this is a local variable and it's not used after this memset
编译器意识不到
the compiler isn't going to realize that
这个和这个占用相同的内存空间
this is occupying the same memory space as this
它只会觉得为什么要执行
it's just going to see okay why are they making
这些耗时的内存写入等等操作
costly operations memory writes and all of this crap
为了一个永远不会被用到的变量
to a variable that's never gonna be used
我们把它去掉吧
let's just remove it
让我给你看看这个
let me show you this
让我们回到
let's get back our
让我们启用优化
okay and let's enable optimizations
这是一个很高的优化级别
this is a high level of optimizations
我必须禁用一个优化
I have to disable one optimization
不是因为它会使我说的不成立
because not that it breaks this fundamentally
只是内联函数使栈不对齐，因此很难演示
but it inline functions  disalligns the stack  so it's harder to demonstrate
使用这些优化编译它
compile it with these optimizations
然后运行它
and run it
又看到了我们的flag
and there's our flag again
为什么？因为GCC拿掉了对memset的调用
why because GCC took out the call to memset
不优化时我们可以看到
we can see it without optimizations
如果我们objdump 看一下
if we object dump
我们看一下main
and we look in main
嗯，在foo中
um in foo
我们看到了对memset的调用
we see the call to memset
如果我们看一下
if we look at
开启优化后
optimizations turned on
我们看一下foo
and we look at foo
没有memset调用
no memset call
我看到它还做了很多其它事
I see a lot of other weird stuff being done
但是没有memset调用
but no memset call
所以它优化掉了很多东西
so it optimized a bunch of stuff away
最终它优化掉了系统的安全性
it optimize the way the security
这种情况经常发生
this actually happens a lot
在加密库实现中真有这种漏洞，它导致了密钥泄露
it's a real vulnerability class in crypto implementations that lead to key disclosures
所以当你写代码的时候要小心
so when you're writing code be careful about that
当然正确的解决方法
the correct fix here of course
在程序开始时将此缓冲区初始化为零
is to initialize this buffer to zero at the start of the program
所以你应该在函数的开始
so you should all at the start of the function
所以你总是应该
so you should always
在使用变量之前初始化代码中的变量
initialize variables in your code before they are used
太棒了，嗯，我们要谈论的数据泄露漏洞就是这些
awesome that um is it for the data disclosure vulnerabilities we'll talk about here
当然还有任意复杂的组合
of course there are arbitrarily complex ones
你可以覆盖指针，然后将它用作读取等等
you could overwrite pointers that are then used as a read etc etc
但是这些简单的方法可以帮助你开始
but these are some simple ones to get you started
我希望你们喜欢内存错误模块
I hope you have enjoyed memory errors and
祝你在作业上好运
good luck on the challenge problems